[Music]
hello YouTube this is Douglas and I'm
back after a semester of working hard at
College in this video I'd like to share
some fascinating experiments that I
performed using distance fields for
Accelerated voxel rendering
specifically I'll be talking about how I
solve the issue of generating these
voxel distance fields in real time using
the GPU rasterizer I also intend to
share how this connects to my voxel
engine at large and about my personal
plans moving forward
as a computer Graphics Enthusiast in the
voxel game engine community
rendering voxels on screen is one of the
most compelling challenges to me
the regular cubic structure of voxels
means that it's possible to employ a
host of rendering techniques that would
not work with the Triangular meshes
typically found in gains
these applications range from pure
rasterization to pure Ray marching where
one advances Rays from the camera until
a voxel is hit
today we'll be exploring a pure Ray
marching technique distance fields or
DFS for short
a DF is a way to either Define or
accelerate Ray intersection tests with
some geometry
dfsr functions which assign every point
in space a number that represents the
distance to the closest surface of solid
geometry
DS can be defined implicitly using
mathematical functions or generated in a
discretized form often signed distance
fields are used where the inside of
geometry has a negative distance to the
surface and outside positive
the sign is not important for my
application though so my tests were
performed with unsigned distance fields
all right so imagine for a moment that
we are given a DF
how might we render the geometry
described by the field
here an algorithm known as sphere
tracing may be applied
sphere tracing is array marching
technique
and follows the same core algorithm as
most others
for each pixel start array at the camera
origin
Advance the ray forward and check if an
intersection occurred
if so color the current pixel otherwise
continue advancing
the question becomes then how far to
advance the ray
this is where the distance field comes
into play
recall the definition of a DF
it's the nearest possible distance to
surface geometry
in other words the DF tells us that
there's no geometry within a sphere of
certain radius centered at the sample
Point hence sphere tracing
as such we know that we can always step
our Ray by the value of the DF at the
current rate position
the same technique can be applied to
voxel scenes
for any voxel grid we simply compute the
distance field for the empty space
around the voxels
[Music]
during rain marching we sample this
distance field in order to determine how
many steps to take
this setup reduces the number of steps
required for rainmarging dramatically
because rays are able to Traverse the
empty space much faster
because the DF can be represented as a
flat array or Texture it's much quicker
to sample than something like an OCT
tree
applying this technique on gpus
therefore leads to far fewer memory
reads and faster performance
there's one small technical difference
between sphere tracing and the voxel
algorithm I'm describing here
in sphere tracing the DF typically gives
you the euclidean distance to the
nearest surface
but for voxels and DDA it makes more
sense to measure the biggest possible
Cube you can draw rather than sphere
this corresponds to taking the infinity
Norm or the maximum component of
displacement rather than the two Norm
for the remainder of this video this is
the type of DF that I'll be discussing
other YouTubers have applied DS and
attempts to improve their engines
and they agree that they are crazy fast
to render
but there's one observation that they
also make
generating DFS for voxel volumes
efficiently is a big challenge
for dynamic scenes it's necessary to be
able to update DS in real time within a
small fraction of a second
pause and Ponder for a moment how you
might Implement such an algorithm
there's an naive approach of iterating
over every voxel and for each voxel
iterating over all of the nearby voxels
to find the closest one
the problem is if you have a total of n
cubed voxels and search up Decay voxels
away this value K is called the kernel
then the runtime of the algorithm is O
of n cubed times K cubed
running this on every voxel in the scene
is slow even if you parallelize things
faster algorithms do exist
I am aware of a dynamic programming
approach that produces the maximal DF
when k equals infinity in only o of n
cubed time
this is theoretically optimal however
the algorithm is not parallelizable and
can only be run on a CPU
as such it is not suited for real-time
processing
I am also aware of an O of n Cube log K
solution which can be faster than the
first algorithm in practice
again though it's not completely
parallelizable
as such these CPU algorithms won't be
the focus of today
I'm happy to make a video in the future
if people are interested however
so back to the problem at hand
how can we efficiently create a DF with
a reasonably large K say 8 or 16 voxels
in real time
it turns out that we can improve the
naive approach and run it on even an
integrated GPU
the key to this is to turn the problem
inside out and Leverage What gpus do
best in the process
rasterization
note that there's actually a second way
to perform the naive approach
in lieu of iterating over every empty
voxel and searching for solid cubes
around it we can do the opposite
we iterate over all solid voxels and
update all empty voxels nearby within a
radius of K with the current solid
voxel's distance
produces the same result but paves the
way for a key optimization
observe that in the typical Ray marching
application we don't need to know any DF
data for solid voxels since the camera
is always outside of the geometry no
rays will be tracing through it anyway
as such we actually only need to iterate
over the solid voxels that lie on the
outside on the surface of our geometry
this has the same result again but
lowers us down in entire Dimension and
simplifies the algorithm
this is still potentially slow
for each surface voxel we need to
explore all voxels in the area around it
and perform a distance calculation for
each surrounding voxel
then we need to update the voxel DF
value accordingly
task is actually perfectly suited to the
GPU
think about drawing a quad
the GPU iterates over all pixels within
the quad calculates a value for each of
them and then updates a frame buffer
with color blending enabled it's even
possible to combine the values produced
by overlapping quads
forms the following algorithm for fast
GPU side DF generation
first we determine all of the voxels on
the surface of our value
with a structure like an oak tree this
is reasonably quick
next for each surface voxel we tell the
GPU to render a set of quads into our
three-dimensional distance field buffer
these quads form a cube with side length
2K minus 1 around the current voxel and
in the fragment Shader for the quads we
calculate the proper DF value
then we use Min blending in order to
take the minimum value of all quads
rendered from various surface voxels
this produces a DF of Kernel size K like
this one
since this process heavily takes
advantage of the gpu's rasterization and
blending Hardware it's fast even on my
Intel integrated graphics
to see whether this concept would
improve rendering I implemented a quick
demo in my voxel engine which you can
see on screen now
it is rendered using pure Ray marching
on a DF
on my Intel integrated GPU the DF
generation time for newly loaded chunks
is between 15 to 30 milliseconds CPU
side and 10 to 20 milliseconds GPU side
this can be improved with caching and
multi-threading but I think it is an
impressive proof of concept
please feel free to check out the online
version of this demo which is linked in
the description
initially when I began experimenting
with distance Fields I was hoping to
come up with something that would match
the performance of Parallax Ray marching
but reduce the complexity
unfortunately I have found that Parallax
Ray marching still outperforms my DF
demo in a significant number of cases
as such I don't plan on integrating a DF
renderer into my engine at the current
time
all is not for naught though while
working on this project I discovered a
faster way to Traverse my voxel octares
which can be applied when generating
meshes for Parallax marching
further I get to share this awesome
technique with all of you
before I end today's video I want to
share a bit about my life and the status
of the voxel engine
first and foremost thanks to everyone
for helping me reach 2500 subscribers
I appreciate the enormous amount of
support and cannot wait to continue
producing high quality voxel content for
all of you
these past few months I haven't been
able to release any new videos because
I've been studying at college
however it's Thanksgiving break this
week so I have some more free time to
work on the engine
happy Turkey Day to all of my fellow
Freedom Lovers by the way
coming up I intend to actually rewrite
the entirety of my engine in order to
increase code cleanliness and modularity
the code compile times have become
extremely long a cold debug build of my
project takes over 30 seconds which is
completely unacceptable
don't even ask how long a release build
takes I'll be rewriting my event system
geese and then splitting my project up
into a cargo workspace with smaller
crates this should allow the rust
compiler an incremental Linker to work
faster
if you want to hear more about that then
stay tuned for the next episode and
don't forget to leave a like And
subscribe
feel free to leave a comment down below
as well I always love answering
questions about voxels
until then thanks for watching and have
a lovely day
[Music]